<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>Concerning imposition of hands A sermon a the Lord Archbishop his visitation metropolitical, held, at Saint Marie Cray in Kent, by the Bishop of Rochester his Graces commissioner, the 7 of September last, preached by Richard Milborne Doctor of Diuinitie, and parson of Seuenoke in Kent.</title>
            <author>Milbourne, Richard, d. 1624.</author>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <edition>
               <date>1607</date>
            </edition>
         </editionStmt>
         <extent>Approx. 49 KB of XML-encoded text transcribed from 27 1-bit group-IV TIFF page images.</extent>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Text Creation Partnership,</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Ann Arbor, MI ; Oxford (UK) :</pubPlace>
            <date when="2011-12">2011-12 (EEBO-TCP Phase 2).</date>
            <idno type="DLPS">A07535</idno>
            <idno type="STC">STC 17917</idno>
            <idno type="STC">ESTC S100306</idno>
            <idno type="EEBO-CITATION">99836151</idno>
            <idno type="PROQUEST">99836151</idno>
            <idno type="VID">405</idno>
            <availability>
               <p>To the extent possible under law, the Text Creation Partnership has waived all copyright and related or neighboring rights to this keyboarded and encoded edition of the work described above, according to the terms of the CC0 1.0 Public Domain Dedication (http://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/). This waiver does not extend to any page images or other supplementary files associated with this work, which may be protected by copyright or other license restrictions. Please go to https://www.textcreationpartnership.org/ for more information about the project.</p>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <seriesStmt>
            <title>Early English books online.</title>
         </seriesStmt>
         <notesStmt>
            <note>(EEBO-TCP ; phase 2, no. A07535)</note>
            <note>Transcribed from: (Early English Books Online ; image set 405)</note>
            <note>Images scanned from microfilm: (Early English books, 1475-1640 ; 1354:19)</note>
         </notesStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <biblFull>
               <titleStmt>
                  <title>Concerning imposition of hands A sermon a the Lord Archbishop his visitation metropolitical, held, at Saint Marie Cray in Kent, by the Bishop of Rochester his Graces commissioner, the 7 of September last, preached by Richard Milborne Doctor of Diuinitie, and parson of Seuenoke in Kent.</title>
                  <author>Milbourne, Richard, d. 1624.</author>
               </titleStmt>
               <extent>[52] p.   </extent>
               <publicationStmt>
                  <publisher>Printed [by I. Windet] for Matthew Law, and are to bee sold at his shop dwelling at the signe of the Fox in Pauls church yard[,</publisher>
                  <pubPlace>London :</pubPlace>
                  <date>1607]</date>
               </publicationStmt>
               <notesStmt>
                  <note>Signatures: A-C[-A1] D⁴[-D4].</note>
                  <note>Printer from STC; publication date from colophon.</note>
                  <note>"A second title page, printed on signature D4r, no doubt intended as a cancel, with 'Motropolitical' corrected to 'Metropolitical' and 'Grace' to 'Graces'."--NUC Pre-1956.</note>
                  <note>A8 mended, affecting a few words of text; some print faded.</note>
                  <note>Reproduction of original in the Union Theological Seminary (New York, N.Y.). Library.</note>
               </notesStmt>
            </biblFull>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>Created by converting TCP files to TEI P5 using tcp2tei.xsl,
      TEI @ Oxford.
      </p>
         </projectDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
            <p>EEBO-TCP is a partnership between the Universities of Michigan and Oxford and the publisher ProQuest to create accurately transcribed and encoded texts based on the image sets published by ProQuest via their Early English Books Online (EEBO) database (http://eebo.chadwyck.com). The general aim of EEBO-TCP is to encode one copy (usually the first edition) of every monographic English-language title published between 1473 and 1700 available in EEBO.</p>
            <p>EEBO-TCP aimed to produce large quantities of textual data within the usual project restraints of time and funding, and therefore chose to create diplomatic transcriptions (as opposed to critical editions) with light-touch, mainly structural encoding based on the Text Encoding Initiative (http://www.tei-c.org).</p>
            <p>The EEBO-TCP project was divided into two phases. The 25,368 texts created during Phase 1 of the project (2000-2009), initially available only to institutions that contributed to their creation, were released into the public domain on 1 January 2015. The approximately 40,000 texts produced during Phase 2 (2009- ), of which 34,963 had been released as of 2020, originally similarly restricted, were similarly freed from all restrictions on 1 August 2020. As of that date anyone is free to take and use these texts for any purpose (modify them, annotate them, distribute them, etc.). But we do respectfully request that due credit and attribution be given to their original source.</p>
            <p>Users should be aware of the process of creating the TCP texts, and therefore of any assumptions that can be made about the data.</p>
            <p>Text selection was based on the New Cambridge Bibliography of English Literature (NCBEL). If an author (or for an anonymous work, the title) appears in NCBEL, then their works are eligible for inclusion. Selection was intended to range over a wide variety of subject areas, to reflect the true nature of the print record of the period. In general, first editions of a works in English were prioritized, although there are a number of works in other languages, notably Latin and Welsh, included and sometimes a second or later edition of a work was chosen if there was a compelling reason to do so.</p>
            <p>Image sets were sent to external keying companies for transcription and basic encoding. Quality assurance was then carried out by editorial teams in Oxford and Michigan. 5% (or 5 pages, whichever is the greater) of each text was proofread for accuracy and those which did not meet QA standards were returned to the keyers to be redone. After proofreading, the encoding was enhanced and/or corrected and characters marked as illegible were corrected where possible up to a limit of 100 instances per text. Any remaining illegibles were encoded as &lt;gap&gt;s. Understanding these processes should make clear that, while the overall quality of TCP data is very good, some errors will remain and some readable characters will be marked as illegible. Users should bear in mind that in all likelihood such instances will never have been looked at by a TCP editor.</p>
            <p>The texts were encoded and linked to page images in accordance with level 4 of the TEI in Libraries guidelines.</p>
            <p>Copies of the texts have been issued variously as SGML (TCP schema; ASCII text with mnemonic sdata character entities); displayable XML (TCP schema; characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or text strings within braces); or lossless XML (TEI P5, characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or TEI g elements).</p>
            <p>Keying and markup guidelines are available at the <ref target="http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/.">Text Creation Partnership web site</ref>.</p>
         </editorialDecl>
         <listPrefixDef>
            <prefixDef ident="tcp"
                       matchPattern="([0-9\-]+):([0-9IVX]+)"
                       replacementPattern="http://eebo.chadwyck.com/downloadtiff?vid=$1&amp;page=$2"/>
            <prefixDef ident="char"
                       matchPattern="(.+)"
                       replacementPattern="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/textcreationpartnership/Texts/master/tcpchars.xml#$1"/>
         </listPrefixDef>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <langUsage>
            <language ident="eng">eng</language>
         </langUsage>
         <textClass>
            <keywords scheme="http://authorities.loc.gov/">
               <term>Sermons, English --  17th century.</term>
            </keywords>
         </textClass>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change>
            <date>2010-04</date>
            <label>TCP</label>Assigned for keying and markup</change>
         <change>
            <date>2010-04</date>
            <label>SPi Global</label>Keyed and coded from ProQuest page images</change>
         <change>
            <date>2010-06</date>
            <label>Megan Marion</label>Sampled and proofread</change>
         <change>
            <date>2010-06</date>
            <label>Megan Marion</label>Text and markup reviewed and edited</change>
         <change>
            <date>2011-06</date>
            <label>pfs</label>Batch review (QC) and XML conversion</change>
      </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text xml:lang="eng">
      <front>
         <div type="title_page">
            <pb facs="tcp:405:1" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <p>CONCERNING Impoſition of hands.</p>
            <p>A Sermon at the Lord Archbi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhop his viſitation Metropolitical, held, at Saint Marie Cray in Kent, by the Biſhop of Rocheſter his Graces Commiſſioner, the 7 of September laſt,</p>
            <p>Preached by <hi>Richard Milborne</hi> Doctor of Diuinitie, and Parſon of Seuen-oke in Kent.</p>
            <p>LONDON Printed for Matthew Law, and are to bee ſold at his ſhop dwelling at the ſigne of the Fox in Pauls Church yard.</p>
         </div>
         <div type="to_the_reader">
            <pb facs="tcp:405:2"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:405:2"/>
            <head>To the Reader.</head>
            <p>
               <seg rend="decorInit">T</seg>He Preacher of this ſer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mon vnwilling to any and vtterly vnwitting of this edition, could not pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miſe either preface praepa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ritoy to the Reader, or Epistle dedicato<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rie to any Perſonage: yet without his leaue it was thought fit for the preſſe, both in reſpect of the ſubiect which it principally handleth, and alſo that the worlde may take knowledge, that (making no compa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>riſon) there is to be found euen in rurall pariſhes both ſufficiency for imployment, and ſoundnes for iudgement, and abilitie for gouernment, <hi>Nam et hic quoque Dij ſunt,</hi> ſaith Heraclitus. It is their
<pb facs="tcp:405:3"/>
greefe indeed, who through neglect lay ſo obſcured, and their plea none other, but theirs in the goſpell, <hi>Nemo nos con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>duxit,</hi> but withall their comfort that it is not the paſſage of this age alone, for both <hi>Salomon</hi> in his time complained of it, that while meaner qualities were aduan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ced, better deſerts went a foote, and their riding experience teacheth them, that braſen ſtirrops muſt helpe men to horſeback, and ſupport them in the ſaddle.</p>
         </div>
      </front>
      <body>
         <div type="sermon">
            <pb facs="tcp:405:3"/>
            <epigraph>
               <q>
                  <bibl>1. Timoth. 5.22.</bibl>
                  <p>Lay hands ſudden<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly on no man, neither bee partaker of other mens ſinnes: keepe thy ſelfe pure.</p>
               </q>
            </epigraph>
            <p>
               <seg rend="decorInit">A</seg>S the whole Scrip<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture in generall is accompted <hi>Specu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lum Chriſtianiſimi,</hi> Iam. 1.23. a look<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing glaſſe for all Chriſtians, wherein they may ſee what they are by na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture, and what they ought to bee by grace:<note place="margin">Ierom. ad Occa.</note> So this Epiſtle in particuler is tearmed of the Fathers, <hi>Speculum cle<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ri,</hi> or <hi>Sacerdotii,</hi> a true ſteale glaſſe, wherein euery Clergie man ought to looke and learne how to faſhion his conuerſation; ſo as it may be ſeemely
<pb facs="tcp:405:4"/>
for himſelfe, gracefull to others, and glorious in the ſight of God. The conſideration hereof hath led mee to the choiſe of this Text: wherein (me thinkes) there is a cleare and full re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>flection of all ſuch affaires, as doe oc<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>caſion this preſent aſſembly: and thoſe I take to be three, according to the clauſes of this verſe. viz. Firſt confirming of faith in ſome, ſecondly reforming of faults in others, and thirdly preſeruing, ſuch a chriſtian puritie in all, as beſt becommeth the Church of Chriſt. Now the perfor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mance of all theſe ſeuerall duties, is peremtorily impoſed vpon <hi>Timothie</hi> the firſt Biſhop of <hi>Epheſus,</hi> either for that impoſition of hands (as it is here taken) was a particuler office of his eminent order, or that hee had abſo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lute authoritie to cenſure the ſinnes of others, or that his integritie was the patterne, by which the behauiour of all beleeuers muſt bee ſquared, as
<pb facs="tcp:405:4"/>
1. <hi>Tim.</hi> 4.12. <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>, Yet is not this direction ſo ſtreictly reſtrained vnto <hi>Timothie,</hi> but that in ſundrie reſpects, it may and ought to bee extended by a rule of neceſſarie conſequence to all his aſſiſtants, for doctrine or diſcipline within his iu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>riſdiction.</p>
            <p>And therefore wee are to eſteeme this as a generall charge giuen to all Church gouernours,<note place="margin">1. <hi>Tim,</hi> 3, 15</note> for their better inſtruction, how to behaue them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelues in the Church of God.</p>
            <p>The whole charge containeth a double prohibition, and a ſingle in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>iunction. The former prohibition tendeth to preuent the raſh imparting of good to others, the latter reſtrai<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neth a voluntarie partaking of euill with others.</p>
            <p>To beginne with the firſt, which is of a narrower compaſſe, and princi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pally reſpecteth <hi>Timothie</hi> and his ſuc<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceſſors: It is ſomewhat darkely ſet
<pb facs="tcp:405:5"/>
downe in a ceremoniall phraſe of <hi>Lay<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing on of hands.</hi> The full vnfolding whereof requireth a threefold enqui<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rie, firſt what was the vſe of impoſing hands, Secondly why it was choſen for ſuch vſe, Thirdly what abuſe hereof is here forbidden. For the firſt <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap> Impoſition of hands, is a ceremonie of great antiquitie, and as it were of gray haires, which hath beene vſed of the Church of God to foure ſpeciall endes, whereupon the ſchoolemen haue giuen it foure di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uers names. <hi>1. Curatoria, 2. Reconcili<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>atoria,</hi> 3. <hi>Ordinatoria,</hi> 4. <hi>Confirmatoria,</hi> for Curing, Reconciling, Ordinati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on, and Confirmation.</p>
            <p>
               <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="1"/> Curatorie impoſion of hands was vſed of ſuch, as had the guift of mi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>raculous healing incurable diſeaſes, this was practiſed by our Sauiour, <hi>Luke,</hi> 4.40. who laid his hands on euery diſeaſed bodie brought vnto him, and healed them, and it was pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miſed
<pb facs="tcp:405:5"/>
to continue for a time in the Church, <hi>Mar.</hi> 16.18. <hi>They ſhall lay their hands on ſicke, and they ſhall reco<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uer;</hi> which afterward was performed in <hi>Ananias,</hi> who reſtored fight to <hi>Saul</hi> by this geſture. <hi>Act. 9.</hi>17. and in <hi>Paul</hi> himſelfe <hi>Act. 28.</hi>8. who ſo cu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red <hi>Publius</hi> his father, of a feauer and a blodie flixe.</p>
            <p>
               <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="2"/> Reconciliatory laying on of hands was vſed, at the publique reconciling and receiuing of <hi>paenitentiaries</hi> into the Church, from which they had departed in the heate of perſecution, or beene caſt out by excommunica<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion, for after the appointed time of their pennance was expired, they were reſtored to the Communion and fellwoſhip of the faithfull, by this meanes, as appeareth <hi>by Ciprian, lib. 3. epiſtola</hi> 14. and the third councell of <hi>Carthage. canon.</hi> 32. <hi>Cuiuſcunque pae<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nitentis publicum &amp; vulgatiſſimum cri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>men eſt, &amp; quod vniuerſam Eccleſiam
<pb facs="tcp:405:6"/>
co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>mouerit, ante abſida 1. atrium Eccleſiae manus eis imponatur.</hi> Alluding, as it ſhould ſeeme, to the cuſtome of pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſenting the ſacrifice vnder the law, ſet downe. <hi>Exod.</hi> 29.10. for as there the Prieſts put their hands vpon the head of the beaſt that was to be ſacrificed, before the Tabernacle of the con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gregation: ſo here a true Penitentiarie is by the like ceremonie preſented as a liuing, reaſonable holy and accepta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble ſacrifice vnto God, at his reſtitu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion vnto the viſible ſocietie of the Saints.</p>
            <p>
               <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="3"/> Ordinatorie Impoſing of hands is a ſacred rite, whereby men were con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſecrated and inueſted into roomes of diuine calling, either in the common wealth, ſo was <hi>Ioſuah</hi> by <hi>Moſes</hi> made Captaine of the hoſt of Iſraell, <hi>Num.</hi> 27.23. or in the Church, ſo were Deacons ordered, <hi>Act.</hi> 6.6. So were <hi>Barnabas</hi> and <hi>Saul</hi> authorized to the worke of their calling among the
<pb facs="tcp:405:6"/>
Gentiles, <hi>Act.</hi> 13.3. And ſo was <hi>Ti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mothie</hi> consecrated a Biſhop by the impoſition of Saint <hi>Paules</hi> hands. 2. <hi>Tim. 1.6.</hi> where that <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap> in <hi>Timothie</hi> is of the ſou<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>deſt interpre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ters vnderſtood to bee nothing elſe, but <hi>functio epiſcopalis &amp; donum prophe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tiae</hi> an Epiſcopall function with the gift of prophecie, and other graces fit for that great place.</p>
            <p>
               <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="4"/> The fourth and laſt kind of <hi>Laying on of handes</hi> is called confirmatorie, becauſe it was vſed with feruent pray<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>er, for the bleſſing of children, or for the ſtrengthning and increaſe of grace, lately begunne in yong profeſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſors of godlineſſe. Thus did <hi>Iocob</hi> bleſſe <hi>Ephraim</hi> and <hi>Manaſſes,</hi> the ſons of <hi>Ioſeph, Gen.</hi> 48.15. whoſe practiſe (being the primitiue patterne of this ſacred ordinance recorded in the ſcripture) is expreſſed at large, both for the circumſtance of <hi>impoſing his handes</hi> on the childrens heads, with
<pb facs="tcp:405:7"/>
particuler reſpect of their future eſt<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ate, as alſo for the ſubſtance of his prayer conceiued for that purpoſe. <hi>God before whome my fathers, Abraham and Iſaac did walke: God which hath fed me all my life long vnto this day, and the Angell which hath deliuered mee from all euill, bleſſe theſe children.</hi> Thus alſo did our bleſſed Sauiour bleſſe thoſe little ones that were brought vnto him. <hi>Mat.</hi> 19.13. with this requeſt, that he would put his hands on them and pray. Thus did <hi>Peter</hi> and <hi>Iohn lay their hands</hi> vpon the Samaritanes lately baptiſed by <hi>Philip</hi> the Euan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>geliſt, that they might receiue a grea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter meaſure of grace <hi>Act.</hi> 8.17. And thus Saint <hi>Paul</hi> confirmed thoſe 12. Epheſians after baptiſme, <hi>Act.</hi> 19.6. And by this rite procured vnto them ſenſible gifts of the holy Ghoſt. Now as the Apoſtles were warranted to the obſeruation of this cuſtome, either by their maſters practiſe or precept, or
<pb facs="tcp:405:7"/>
by ſome ſpeciall direction of Gods ſpirit, whereof they were then fully poſſeſſed, according to Chriſts pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miſe.<note place="margin">Nam nullus homo elfi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cere poteſt vt externu<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> ſymbolum contimeat certam pro miſsionem gratiae, Chemnici<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>us,</note> So they likewiſe commended it vnto the Church, as an holy ordi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nance of perpetuall continuance, in which reſpect <hi>Impoſition of handes</hi> is marſhalled among the fundamentall points of Catechiſme, taught in the primitiue Church, <hi>Heb. 6.</hi>2. So that as repentance from dead workes, faith toward God, the doctrine of baptiſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mes, of the generall reſurrection and eternall iudgement are ſtill to conti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nue: In like ſort is the <hi>laying on of hands</hi> after baptiſme, as there it is placed. And as the Apoſtles of Chriſt left it; ſo it hath for many hundred yeares continued in the chriſtian world, as a ſacred inſtitution of great reputati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on, magnified of the ancient Fathers,<note place="margin">Tertull. Cyprian. Ambr. Auguſt.</note> as a ſinguler meanes to confirme, in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>creaſe, and perfect ſpirituall graces, begun in baptiſme, whereof one
<pb facs="tcp:405:8"/>
ſaith <hi>ſpiritus ſactus,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Euſebius emiſſenus ſermone de penticoſſe,</note> 
               <hi>qui in fonte bap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tiſmi plenitudinem tribuit ad innocen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tiam, in confirmatione augmentum prae<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtat ad gratiam,</hi> the holy Ghoſt, which in the fountaine of Baptiſme giueth that fulnes, that ſufficeth for inno<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cencie, afterwards in confirmation, exhibiteth an augmentation of fur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther grace, neceſſarie for performing the duties of a Chriſtian life, and re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſiſting of all ſinfull temptations, ſo that their common conceit of this ſacramental complement is, that as by baptiſme the faithfull are receiued in <hi>familiam Dei:</hi>
               <note place="margin">Aquia, in ſum part. 3, q, 72 art. 1,</note> ſo by confirmation <hi>cooptantur in militiam Dei,</hi> or as ano<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther ſpeaketh, <hi>in baptiſmo regenera<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mur ad vitam, poſt baptiſmu<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> confirma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mur ad pugnam,</hi> This was the anci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ent account of this religious rite, ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uer impeached for many ages, vntill of late ſome (<hi>Ouer licencious in cenſu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ring the iudgement of antiquitie</hi>) beſides ſundry trifling cauils, haue excepted
<pb facs="tcp:405:8"/>
againſt it in two maine reſpects. Firſt that it is a fruitles ceremonie, becauſe no ſuch manifeſt ſpirituall effects of languages and prophecie, are now at<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tained by it, as were in the dayes of the Apoſtles, But to this imputation Saint <hi>Augustine</hi> anſwered long ago.<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Lib.</hi> 3. cap. 16. de bap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tiſ cont. Donat.</note> 
               <hi>Neque enim temporalibus &amp; ſenſibili<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bus miraculis atteſtantibus, per manus impoſitionem medodatur ſpiritus ſanctus, ſicut antea dabatur ad commendationem rudis fidei, &amp; Eccleſiae primordia dila<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tanda, ſed inuiſibiliter &amp; latenter cordi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bus diuina charitas inſpiratur.</hi> And leaſt any ſhould imagine, this to be but an idle fancie of that Father, it is verie plaine in ſcripture, that God doth v<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſually grace the firſt inſtitution of his ordinances, with extraordinarie to<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>kens of his fauour, which afterwarde ceaſe with out any diſparagement to his ordinance, as at the firſt erection of that <hi>Sanedrin,</hi> or great Councell of ſtate among the Iewes, <hi>Num.</hi> 11.25.
<pb facs="tcp:405:9"/>
euerie one of the ſeuentie Elders pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>phecied for a ſeaſon, to teſtifie that their calling was from heauen; the ſurceaſing of which gift in them and their ſucceſſors, was no derogation to their vocation, being once ſuffici<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ently ratified.</p>
            <p>
               <note place="margin">Leuit. 9.24</note>Moreouer at the firſt inſtitution of the Leuiticall Prieſthood and Sacri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fices, there came a fire out from the Lord, and conſumed vpon the Altar, the burnt offering and the fat; which was not vſuall afterward, ſaue at the eſtabliſhing of Gods worſhip, when the Temple was dedicated, 2. <hi>Chron.</hi> 7.1. and at the reſtoring of religion vpon that generall apoſtaſie in <hi>Elias</hi> his time, 1. <hi>King.</hi> 8.38. Many ſacrifices were well accepted of God, albeit they were not in like ſort conſumed with fire from heauen, as theſe were. So then, as it were ſtrange diuinitie, to affirme that the ſpirit of God doth not now diſcend vpon the waters of ordi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>narie
<pb facs="tcp:405:9"/>
baptiſme, becauſe it is not ſeene in the bodily ſhape of a Doue, where in it came downe vpon Chriſt,<note place="margin">Mat. 3.</note> at his baptiſing; or to hold that in the com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mon miniſterie of the worde prea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ched, the ſpirit is not giuen, becauſe it falleth not viſibly vpon the hearers, as it did at ſaint <hi>Peters</hi> firſt ſermon to the Gentiles, <hi>Act.</hi> 10.44. No leſſe ſtrange is it, to conclude, that there commeth now no increaſe of ſauing grace by confirmation, becauſe im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſition of hands, is not now accom<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>panied with ſuch miraculous effects, as gaue it countenance at the begin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ning. <hi>Miracula ceſſarunt, ne eorum con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſuetudine frigeſceret genus humanum,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Aug, de ver. relig, ca, 25</note> 
               <hi>quorum nouitate flagrauit.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>The ſecond exception taken a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainſt this ſacred ordinance, is in re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gard of the Miniſter thereof, namely a biſhop or chief Paſtor of the church, which breedeth a conceite (ſay they) that it is a more excellent myſterie of
<pb facs="tcp:405:10"/>
religion, then the ſacrament of Bap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tiſme, which may be had at euery in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>feriour Miniſters hands.</p>
            <p>
               <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="1"/> To this it may be replied, <hi>1</hi> That it is a ſpice of refurbiſhed Donatiſme, to value ſacraments or ſacred ordi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nances by the worth of their Mini<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſter. <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="2"/> Secondly, that it hath euer been a cuſtome in the Church of God (which in Saint <hi>Pauls</hi> time was an ar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gument of ſome weight eſpecially in caſes of this condition) that the chiefe Gouernours,<note place="margin">1. Cor, 11 16</note> and ſpirituall Fathers onely haue ordinarily exerciſed this duetie from the firſt inſtitution of it. For when <hi>Iacob</hi> laid his hands on <hi>Io<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſephs</hi> ſonnes, hee was the ancienteſt Patriarch among the people of God; and while Chriſt liued, children were preſented to him alone, not to any of his Diſciples: And after his aſcenſion, none but the Apoſtles con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>firmed thoſe, whom inferior teachers had baptized: and when they had fi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niſhed
<pb facs="tcp:405:10"/>
their courſe,<note place="margin">Act. 8.</note> the charge of <hi>im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſing ha<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ds is committed,</hi> as we ſee here to <hi>Timothie</hi> a Biſhop, and conſequent<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly to others of like preeminence. And this cuſtom ſeemeth to be grounded vpon two ſpeciall reaſons: The firſt whereof is, that whereas the won<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>derfull effects of the Patriarchs bleſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſings vpon their children and poſte<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ritie, hath bred an opinion in all the world, that there is ſomewhat more in a naturall fathers bleſsing, then in another mans, either for that God more reſpecteth the dignitie of his place, or the zeale of his affection to<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ward the party for whom he prayeth: euen ſo it is as probable, that a ſpiri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tuall Fathers prayer, is moſt powerful to procure bleſsings vnto the childre<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> of the Church, who in dignitie of place commeth nearer vnto God, and for zealous deuotion is ſuppoſed far to exceede any naturall father, yea al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>though he be <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap> as S. <hi>Iames,</hi>
               <pb facs="tcp:405:11"/>
ſpeaketh of <hi>Elias</hi> ſubiect to paſsions like other men,<note place="margin">Iam. 5.17</note> yet his feruent prayer auayleth much.</p>
            <p>
               <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="2"/> A ſecond reaſon, why confirmation hath euer ordinarily beene miniſtred by Biſhops, I take to bee this, that as the holy Ghoſt hath placed a prelacie in the Church, according to S. <hi>Paules</hi> aſſertion, <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap> to bee Preſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dents and preſeruers of vnitie and peace among Gods people, for other<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wiſe there would be <hi>Tot ſchiſmata, quot Sacerdotes:</hi>
               <note place="margin">Acts 20.28 Ierom.</note> ſo by the wiſedome of the ſame ſpirit, ſome duties (where<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>upon the peace of the Church doth chiefly depend) are reſerued to that order, of which ſort are theſe. <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="1"/> Firſt dedication of Churches, becauſe all Schiſmatiques doe affect priuate con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uenticles for exerciſes of Religion, it hath beene concluded, that no place ſhould be licenced for the publique ſeruice of God, but ſuch as the Bi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhop of the Dioceſſe ſhould allowe.
<pb facs="tcp:405:11"/>
               <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="2"/> Secondly, in regard that diuerſitie of Teachers often cauſeth diſtraction a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mong profeſſors, as <hi>1. Cor.</hi> 12. <hi>I am Pauls, I am Apollos, I am Cephas;</hi> for auoi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding hereof, none are to vndertake a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny worke of the Miniſtrie, but ſuch as are ordained or licenced by the Ordi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>narie of the place where they liue. <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="3"/> Thirdly, forſomuch as varietie of bap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tizers occaſioneth faction and ſingu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>laritie of conceyte among beleeuers,<note place="margin">1. Cor. 1.14</note> which mooued Saint <hi>Paul</hi> to thanke God, that hee had baptized ſo few of the Corinthians; for preuenting of diſcord in this reſpect, the wiſedome of Gods Church hath iudged it ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceſſarie, that all her children after baptiſme receiued in ſundry places, &amp; by diuers inferior perſons, ſhould in conuenient time, be preſented vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to the chiefe Paſtor and peſeruer of Peace in Gods family, who might e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>qually ratifie their ingrafting into the myſticall bodie of Chriſt, &amp; acknow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ledge
<pb facs="tcp:405:12"/>
them indifferently to bee the children of the Church, and pray re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſpectiuely for increaſe of faith, and o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther ſauing graces in them all. And thus much for the vſe of this ceremo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nie in religious affaires. Next we are to conſider, why it was choſen for ſuch purpoſes.</p>
            <p>
               <note place="margin">Delectus.</note>Now for the better vnderſtanding hereof we are to know, that as in na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture the ſoul frameth a body fit for his imployment and operation, ſo dooth the ſpirit of God make choice of ſuch Elements and Ceremonies, as doe moſt liuely repreſent the benefites to bee conueyed by them, as of water for baptiſme, and bread and wine for the Lords Supper. The like is to bee thought of this Ceremonie, which hath continued immutable in the manifold abrogations &amp; ſhipwracks of many other rites, that there is in it ſuch a proportion with the ſpirituall bleſsing deriued by it, as is moſt fit
<pb facs="tcp:405:12"/>
to inſtruct, and affect the faithfull in all ages, which may bee thus con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceiued.</p>
            <p>In the <hi>Pſalme</hi> 77.30. it is ſaide, that <hi>God did lead his people like ſheepe, by the hand of Moſes and Aaron.</hi> So that the Magiſtrates <hi>hand,</hi> whether it bee ciuill or eccleſiaſticall, is accounted the <hi>hand</hi> of God, whoſe Vicegerents they bee.</p>
            <p>
               <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="1"/> Firſt then, when any ſpiritual grace is receiued, or any place is beſtowed in the Church, or Common-wealth, by <hi>laying on of hands,</hi> it plainely teſt<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>fieth, whence men receiue ſuch fauours. It was the hand of God that gaue them this or that grace, that ſet them in ſuch and ſuch place. <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="2"/> Secondly, be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cauſe the protection of the Church is aſcribed to Gods <hi>hand,</hi> ſo long as men continue faithfull in their cal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lings,<note place="margin">Pſal. 44 3</note> and thankfull for the graces ob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tained, they may be ſecured of Gods defence &amp; aſsiſtance, againſt all diffi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>culties
<pb facs="tcp:405:13"/>
&amp; dangers, that ſhall encoun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter them in their vocation. <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="3"/> Thirdly, as the <hi>hand</hi> of God is mightie to main<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>taine the good: ſo is it pote<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>t to puniſh the bad, whether they bee ſtrangers from the couenant, as the <hi>hand</hi> of God was heauy vpon the Philiſtims of Aſhdod,<note place="margin">1. Sam. 5: 6.</note> for prophaning the Arke, or the children of the Church, as the Prophet complaineth, <hi>Pſal.</hi> 32.4. <hi>Thy hand is heauie vpon me day and night,</hi> for abuſing that high place, and great grace, which hee had receyued. The conſideration wherof ought to curbe all mens conſciences in theſe caſes. And this is the ſenſe, and as it were the life of this Ceremonie.</p>
            <p>
               <label type="milestone">
                  <seg type="milestoneunit">Abuſes. </seg>
               </label> The abuſe here prohibited, com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>meth thirdly to be examined, which the Apoſtle noteth vſually to fall out by the ſuddaine exerciſe of it. Indeed ſuddain reſolutions are ſeldom ſound.<note place="margin">Eccle. 3.11.</note> The wiſe man affirmeth that God made euerie thing beautifull in his
<pb facs="tcp:405:13"/>
time. Now this <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap> argueth a de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fect of due time, and conſequently a deformitie in this action. Haſte in ſome religious duties doth well, and is very come<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ndable, as in repentance. <hi>Pſal.</hi> 119.60. <hi>I made haſte, and delaied not to keepe thy commandements.</hi> In heating Gods worde, <hi>Iam.</hi> 1.19. <hi>Let euerie man be ſwift to heare.</hi> In performing vowes, <hi>Eccle.</hi> 5.3. <hi>When thou haſt vowed to God, deferre not to pay.</hi> And others of that nature, in which as <hi>Cyprian</hi> ſaid (whe<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> he was halled to his martyrdome) <hi>In rebus ſacris nulla eſt deliberatio.</hi> But there bee other ſacred acti<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> is of a doubtfull ſequell, wherein ha<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap>e is ve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rie hurtfull and reproueable, as the Apoſtle teſtifieth, admoniſhing to be ſlow to ſpeake, and ſlow to anger.<note place="margin">Iam. <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>.19.</note> In theſe and ſome other of like condi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> (wherof <hi>impoſition of hands</hi> is one) we may ſay with <hi>Salomon, Prou.</hi> 19, 2. <hi>Qui feſtinat uon pedibus ſed manibus pec<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cat.</hi> 
               <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="1"/> And that <hi>1.</hi> againſt him who im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſeth
<pb facs="tcp:405:14"/>
               <hi>hands;</hi>
               <note place="margin">Non decit.</note> for it neither beſeemeth his wiſdome, being the high ſteward in Gods houſe,<note place="margin">Luk. 12.42</note> to giue them their al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lowance out of ſeaſon, nor the grauity of his calling; for as he commeth near to the higheſt in place, ſo ought he to bee moſt deliberate in his procee<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dings, like the higheſt Planets that bee of the ſloweſt and moſt regular motion; nor the reuerent regard hee ought to haue of this ſacred ordi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nance, for there is no fruitfull <hi>lay<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing on of handes,</hi> without a lifting vp of handes in ſolemne prayer, which neceſſa<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap>y requireth a pauſe, <hi>Eccle. 5.1. <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>it not thy mouth be raſh, nor thy heart <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>aſtie to vtter a thing before God.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <note place="margin">No<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> expedit</note> 
               <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="2"/> Secondly, ſudde<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> 
               <hi>impoſition of hands</hi> is not expedient for ſuch as they are laid on, <hi>Virtus agentis eſt ex natura recipie<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>tis,</hi> ſaith the Philoſopher, and experience teacheth it to bee true, in the contrary effects of the Suns heate, in wax and clay: wherefore if the party on whom
<pb facs="tcp:405:14"/>
               <hi>hands are laid,</hi> bee not capable of the grace, thereby offered, it fareth with him as with olde bottels, in which new wine is put: &amp; this was the cauſe of thoſe preparatiue ſanctifications before the participatio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> of holy things in the time of the law, <hi>Exod.</hi> 19 10.<note place="margin">Mat. 9.17</note> 
               <hi>Ito ad populum &amp; ſanctifica eus hodie &amp; cras,</hi> ſaith God to <hi>Moſes</hi> before the giuing of the law.<note place="margin">Iob 1 5</note> And <hi>Iob</hi> firſt ſanctified his ſonnes, and then ſacrificed for them. <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="3"/> Thirdly, haſtie <hi>laying on of hands</hi> is vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lawfull in regarde of all the ſpeciall ends, for which it was vſed.<note place="margin">Non licet.</note>
            </p>
            <p>
               <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="1"/> For firſt if it were <hi>ad curandum,</hi> there is a time neceſſarily required to conſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der whether the patient haue faith to be healed,<note place="margin">Act, 14 9.</note> as S. <hi>Paul</hi> did ere he cured the lame man at Lyſtra.</p>
            <p>
               <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="2"/> If <hi>ad reconciliandum,</hi> the trial of true repe<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>tance was with all diligence to be made, which cannot be diſcerned vpo<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> a ſudden, leaſt hee that was looſed in earth, ſhould remain bound in heaue<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>.
<pb facs="tcp:405:15"/>
The former ages haue beene verie cautelous and circumſpect in this point, and therefore they meaſured out the time of repentance, accor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding to the qualitie of mens offen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ces, for to ſome they enjoyned it, for the ſpace of three yeares, to o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thers for ſeuen yeares, to others for ten yeares, to other for thirteen years, as appeareth by the 11. Canon of the 1. Nicene Councell, intituled <hi>De his qui ſponte lapſi ſunt, qualiter debeant poenitere.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="3"/> If <hi>Ad confirmandum, handes muſt not be laid on,</hi> before children be there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vnto prepared, vntill they be ſeaſoned with the rudiments of Religion, and bee capable of exhortation, not to receiue the grace of God in vaine, nor turne it into wantonneſſe, but that they bee carefull to grow vp in true godlineſſe, according to the grounds thereof, laid and learned in their tender yeares.</p>
            <pb facs="tcp:405:15"/>
            <p>
               <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="4"/> If <hi>ad Ordinandum,</hi> what a long time is neceſſarie to examine the ſuffici<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>encie of men for that calling, vnto which ſo few are ſufficient <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>? ſaith the Apoſtle, 2. <hi>Cor.</hi> 2.16. who can ſuddainely tell what skill they haue <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>,<note place="margin">2 Tim. 2.15</note> to diuide the word of truth aright? or to ſpeake a ſeaſonable word to the weary ſoule? or who knoweth without long triall, what grace they haue <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>,<note place="margin">Gal. 2.14</note> to walke with a right foote according to the truth of the Goſpell?</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Nazianzene</hi> in his Apologie, com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pares the courſe of a Cleargie mans life to a Tumblers walking vppon a corde, whoſe ſafetie conſiſteth <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>, in an exact euen carriage of his bodie, for the leaſt ſwaying to ei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther ſide is no little hazard of his life. So if a Cleargie man (ſaith he) ſwarue on either hand <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>, A ſmall ſlip of his, either in
<pb facs="tcp:405:16"/>
faith or maners, procureth no ſmall danger both to himſelfe and thoſe ouer whom he is placed. This was it that mooued the faithfull in the pri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mitiue Church to ſuch praier and fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſting,<note place="margin">Act, 13.3,</note> before they <hi>laid hands on any</hi> for ordination; and this was it that af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>terward cauſed thoſe <hi>Ieiunia</hi> 4. <hi>tempo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rum,</hi> the quarter faſts of ember weeks to bee yeerely kept throughout all Chriſtendome, and a decree to bee made, that no Eccleſiaſticall orders ſhould bee Canonicall, which were not giuen on the Sabbath dayes next enſuing one of theſe ſet and ſolemne faſts, as if the moſt deuout prayers of the whole Catholike Church were requiſite to beg a competent bleſsing for this holy iunction.</p>
            <p>Thus we haue the contents of the firſt prohibition, reſtraining the raſh imparting of good to others. Now let vs ſee the ſecond, which ſeemeth to be of a larger extent, in forbidding
<pb facs="tcp:405:16"/>
the preſumptuous partaking of euill <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="2"/> with others. <hi>Neither be partaker of o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther mens ſinnes. Vitia ſerpunt ad vici<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nos, &amp; contactu nocent,</hi> (ſaith <hi>Seneca</hi>) ſinnes are like plague ſores, which breath out an infectious ſteame to all by ſtanders: ſo then for the fuller o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pening of this point we muſt firſt co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
               <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſider, by what paſſages, vices creepe from one to another, and infect. Se<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>condly, <hi>quomodo nocent,</hi> how they hurt or endanger others by their in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fection. For the firſt, as the Lawyers make two ſortes of acceſſaries, one before the fact or offence committed, another after: ſo the ſame diuiſion will ſtand well in Diuinitie; for ſinne is like the ſerpent <hi>Amphiſbaena,</hi> which hath one ſting in the head, and ano<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther in the taile, and powreth our poiſon at both endes, and that <hi>ore triſulco,</hi> with a three forked ſting; for before the working of any wickednes others may bee partakers of it three
<pb facs="tcp:405:17"/>
wayes, 1. <hi>iubendo,</hi> 2. <hi>prou<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>c<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ndo.</hi> 3. <hi>conſulendo.</hi>
               <note place="margin">Direct precept word or</note> 
               <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="1"/> Firſt, by commaunding, other mens ſinnes become ours, and that eyther by direct precept of word, as the murther of the Lords prieſtes is imputed vnto king <hi>Saul, 1. Sam.</hi> 22.21. becauſe he bad <hi>Doeg</hi> the Edomite fall vpon them:<note place="margin">writte,</note> or of Writ, as the kil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ling of <hi>Vriah</hi> the Hittite, is laid to king <hi>Dauids</hi> charge, 2. <hi>Sam.</hi> 12. <hi>Tu occidiſti Vriam gladio:</hi> For that <hi>Ioab</hi> did ſet <hi>V<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>riah</hi> in the forlorn hope, by <hi>Dauids</hi> di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rection.<note place="margin">Indirect authorizing</note> 
               <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="2"/> Or elſe by indirect autho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rizing of others to worke wickednes: He that puts a ſword in a madde mans hand, is guilty of the miſchiefe com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mitted by it.</p>
            <p>
               <note place="margin">
                  <gap reason="foreign">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap> 
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>unda vel baliſta. Page.</note>This is the meaning of the wiſema<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>, <hi>Prou.</hi> 26.8. when he ſaith <hi>Applicat lapi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dem baliſtae, qui praebet honorem ſtolido:</hi> He putteth a pellet into a ſtone bow to be diſcharged at al aduenture, that ſet<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teth afoole in place of authoritie; the inconuenience whereof is fitly deſcri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bed
<pb facs="tcp:405:17"/>
in the firſt verſe of the ſame Chap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter: <hi>As ſnow in ſummer, and raine in harueſt, ſo is honour vnſeemely for a foole:</hi> for a bad Magiſtrate in the ciuill ſtate, or a wicked gouernour in the church, blaſtern the bloſſome and blade (the hope of future increaſe) and eyther rotteth the ripe finit of Gods harueſt, or elſe neuer lets it come to ripenes, through the vnſeaſonable moiſture of his malignant miſdeameanour.</p>
            <p>
               <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="3"/> 
               <hi>Prouocaando,</hi> by prouocation, wee may draw other mens ſins vpon our ſelues, either by <hi>daring</hi> of them,<note place="margin">Daring.</note> as <hi>Iezabel</hi> vrged <hi>Achab</hi> to the oppreſſion of <hi>Naboth,</hi> 1. <hi>Kings</hi> 21.7. <hi>Tune nunc exerceres regnum ſuper Iſraelem?</hi> for which offence, as the dogges licked <hi>Naboaths</hi> blood, ſo they deuoured her fleſh, 2. <hi>Kings,</hi> 9.36. In like ſorte the common prouocations of others to needles oathes, friuolous contentions, exceſſiue drinking and ſwilling, &amp;c. fall within the compaſſe of this fault.
<pb facs="tcp:405:18"/>
Or by alluring intiſements of profite, as <hi>Prou. 1.</hi>14. <hi>Caſt in thy lot among vs, wee will all haue one purſe.</hi> Or of plea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſure, <hi>Prou.</hi> 7 <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>8. <hi>Come let vs take our fill of loue vntill the morning.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="3"/> 
               <hi>Conſulendo.</hi> Other mens iniquities are made ours by euill counſell gi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uing. So <hi>Balaam</hi> was guilty of the ſtu<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
               <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bling blocke which hee counſelled <hi>Balaack</hi> to put before the children of Iſrael, <hi>Numb.</hi> 24.14. And therefore he ſtumbled vpon the Iſraelites ſword, in his going homeward, <hi>Numb. 31.</hi>8. <hi>Alſo they ſlew Balaam the ſonne of Peor with the ſword.</hi> And ſo ſinned <hi>Achito<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>phel</hi> in aduiſing <hi>Abſolon</hi> to vnnatu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rall luſt, which was none of the leaſt occa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſions, that brought him to an vnnatu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rall end, 2 <hi>Sam.</hi> 16.21.</p>
            <p>Theſe are the paſſages, by which we partake others offences, before they be committed, and as it were, the three forked ſting in the head of ſinne; like vnto which, is that other in the
<pb facs="tcp:405:18"/>
tayle: for after a wickedneſſe is wrought, others may bee acceſſari<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>es vnto it in three reſpects. Firſt, <hi>Conniuendo.</hi> 2. <hi>Conſentiendo.</hi> 3. <hi>De<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fendendo.</hi> 
               <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="1"/> The firſt, Conniuencie, or winking at enormities, is the com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mon ſinne of ſuperiours, to whome a ſworde of authority is committed, <hi>Rom.</hi> 13.4. for cutting off malefactors, therefore, <hi>qui tolerat aliena peccata, cum tollere poſsit, ſua facit.</hi> This was it, which Saint <hi>Paul</hi> ſo ſharpely cenſu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red in the Corinthians,<note place="margin">1. Cor. 5.1.</note> who neglec<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted the rodde of diſcipline againſt the inceſtuous perſon; and this was it, that pulled powne an endleſſe iudge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment on <hi>Eli</hi> his houſe, for that as a Father and chiefe Iudge of Iſrael,<note place="margin">1. Sam, 3 13</note> was by duety and conſcience bound, hee did not iudge his graceleſſe ſonnes, whoſe couetous and laſciuious life brought Religion into extreame con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tempt and diſgrace, 1. <hi>Sam.</hi> 2.17.
<pb facs="tcp:405:19"/>
               <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="2"/>
               <hi>Men abhorred the offering of the Lord.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>Conſent</hi> makes other mens ſinnes ours, whether it be expreſſed in deed, as <hi>Pſ.</hi> 50.18. <hi>When thou ſeeſt a thiefe, thou runneſt with him, and thou art partaker with the adulterers.</hi> Or in word, as 2. Epiſt. <hi>Iohn</hi> 11. verſe. <hi>He that biddeth an Heretique God ſpeed, is partaker of his euil deedes.</hi> Or elſe, if it be by a ſuppreſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſed conſent, for there is <hi>conſenſus ſilen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tii,</hi> when ſinne is not rebuked by thoſe, that are warranted thereunto by ſpeciall calling, according to the commaundement giuen, <hi>Leu.</hi> 19.17 <hi>Thou ſhalt plainely rebuke thy brother, neither ſuffer ſinne to reſt in him:</hi> the rea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſon hereof is, for that as <hi>malum conſili<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>um inducit in peccatum; ita malum ſilenti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>um relinquit in peccato.</hi>
               <note place="margin">Exod. 23, 4,</note> And it is a great want of charitie to deny that fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uour to a man, which muſt be afforded to a bruit beaſt, yea, to an enemies Aſſe. But if a man want a warrant to
<pb facs="tcp:405:19"/>
reproue,<note place="margin">Ezech 9.8.</note> then he muſt mourne for the offence, and pray for the offender, ſo happily hee may eſcape the generall ſcourge when it commeth: otherwiſe, as one ſaith, <hi>Peccatum tuum eſt, quod ti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bi non diſplicet,</hi> in whome ſoeuer it bee.</p>
            <p>
               <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="3"/> The third, laſt and worſt partaking of other mens ſinnes alreadie com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mitted, is <hi>Defendendo,</hi> that is by leſſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ning, excuſing, iuſtifying, or counte<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nancing of them, when men are blin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ded or beſotted with violent paſſions; to extenuate or iuſtifie their own ſin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>full actions, as <hi>Ionas</hi> did his anger,<note place="margin">Ion. 4, 9.</note> is vſuall, but to become a Proctor, or a Patrone of other mens offences (ſee<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing euerie one is naturally prone to miſlike that euill in others which they allow in themſelues) this bee<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wrayes an affection ſtrangely depra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ued and poiſoned with wickedneſſe. <hi>Salomon</hi> caſteth theſe two into an e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quall
<pb facs="tcp:405:20"/>
ballance of abhomination be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore God, <hi>Prou.</hi> 17.15. <hi>to iuſtifie the wicked, and to condemne the iuſt:</hi> and therefore this kinde of iniquity is branded with a double curſe, one of God, Eſay. 5.20. <hi>Woe vnto them that ſpeake good of euill;</hi> another of man, <hi>Prou.</hi> 24.24. <hi>Hee that ſaieth to the wic<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ked thou art righteous, him ſhall the peo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ple curſe, and the multitude ſhall abhorre him.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Thus it appeareth, how other mens vices creepe and infect vs. Now it is to be conſidered, <hi>quomodo nocent,</hi> what hurte commeth by this conta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gion.</p>
            <p>The ſleight regard and ſlender conceit that moſt men haue of their owne miſdeedes, wherein they bee ſole and principall agents, doth eui<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dently ſhew, that they make ſmall, or no conſcience of being acceſſaries to the treſpaſſes wrought by others; but
<pb facs="tcp:405:20"/>
it is the voice of Heauen, <hi>Reuel.</hi> 18.4. That thoſe, that be partakers in ſinnes, ſhall bee partners in plagues; yea, it is a rule of equitie, approued both by naturall and ciuill reaſon, that <hi>acceſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſorium ſequi congruit naturam princpa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lis,</hi> and that aſwell in capitall puniſh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mentes, as monie mulcts; <hi>agentes &amp; conſentientes pari poena plectentur:</hi> Ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cording to the practiſe of all nations in the beſt gouerned ſtates. Now as the execution of this iuſtice in tem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>porall cauſes doth bridle multitudes from much miſchiefe, which other<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wiſe they woulde commit: ſo ought it to curb men much more in caſes of conſcience, eſpecially for theſe two conſiderations. <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="1"/> Firſt, as in mans law, there bee no acceſſaries in ſome of<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fences, but all principals, vz. in trea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſons or attemptes againſt the life of the Prince, and wilfull murthers; So is it to be iudged of all ſinnes what<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſoeuer,
<pb facs="tcp:405:21"/>
for in true conſtruction of Diuinitie, euery ſinne is a wilfull murther of the ſoule. And it is at<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tempted againſt the life of the king of Kinges, becauſe the redemption thereof, coſt the ſonne of God his life. <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="2"/> Secondly, as voluntarie eſcapes amongſt men are puniſhed <hi>lege talio<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nis,</hi> the Keeper or Gaoler wilfullie ſuffering any to eſcape committed to his cuſtody, ſhall ſuffer as in caſe of the partie eſcaped, be it for debt, fel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lony or treaſon. This rule holdes alſo in Gods iuſtice, when a Magi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtrate ſuffers a malefactor to paſſe vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>puniſhed that comes within his com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>paſſe, as it was threatened to king <hi>A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chab,</hi> for letting <hi>Benchadad</hi> goe; whom God had deliuered into his hand to be put to death, being an vnpeaceable foe to the people of God, 1. <hi>King.</hi> 20.42. Becauſe thou haſt let go out of thine handes, a man whom I appoin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted
<pb facs="tcp:405:21"/>
to die, thy life ſhall goe for his life, and thy people for his peo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ple, as it fell out in a ſtraunge fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhion ſhortly after, 1. <hi>Kinges</hi> 22.34. The like ſentence may all men iuſtly feare, who neglect the puniſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment of offences in Church or com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mon wealth, eſpecially being tied thereunto by ſolemne oath, which wrappeth them in a double daunger, one of the ſinne, which they ſhall ſuffer vncenſured; another, of taking Gods name in vaine, which can ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uer eſcape a fearefull affliction.<note place="margin">Lib. 1, cap. 9, de ciuita. Dei.</note> Saint <hi>Auguſtine</hi> ſearching out the ſpeciall reaſons, why in common calamities of warre, famine and plague, good men oftentimes periſh with the bad, ſaith thus; <hi>iure vitam iſtam cum iis amaram ſentiunt, quibus peccantibus a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mari eſſe noluerunt;</hi> They iuſtly taſte the bitterneſſe of Gods wrath, who would not bee bitter in rebuking the
<pb facs="tcp:405:22"/>
publicke tranſgreſſors of his wil. So then to conclude this pointe, wee may verie well affirme, with a re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uerent Father and Martyr of our own Church, that although it be a ſtrange prayer, yet it is as neceſſary a one, as anie man can vſe; O Lord de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liuer mee from my other mens ſinnes.</p>
            <p>
               <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="3"/> The third laſt clauſe of this charge is, an iniunction, exacting the pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſeruation of a particular innocencie in <hi>Timothie</hi> and other his Aſſiſtantes, or equals; <hi>Keepe thy ſelfe pure.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>The keeping of any thing pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſuppoſeth a former poſſeſſion of it, &amp; therefore we are not to doubt, but <hi>Timothie</hi> had attained to a great mea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſure of Chriſtian purity before his conſecration, it being the principall qualitie required in a Biſhoppe, <hi>1. Tim.</hi> 3.2. to bee vnreproueable, <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>, that is, free eyther from
<pb facs="tcp:405:22"/>
all ſuch imputations, as are puniſh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>able with any reproachfull penaltie among men, or elſe not ſubiect to any morall Epilepſies of groſſe ſinnes, which bereaue a man for the time, of all ſenſe and ſhew of true god<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lineſſe.</p>
            <p>Further, this precept, <hi>Keepe thy ſelfe pure,</hi> implieth the continuall purifying of his minde: for as a glaſſe bee it made neuer ſo cleane, will daily gather duſt and motes, if it ſtand in any open place, and there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore needeth continuall wiping: ſo is it with the beſt mans ſoule and conſcience that euer was, if he neglect at any time to purge his heart from ſuggeſted or homebred corruptions.</p>
            <p>Now the purity, which is here inioyned, I take to be twofolde; the firſt locall, as hee was a Biſhoppe, according to that ſpeech of the Pſal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miſt;<note place="margin">Pſal. 93, 5</note> 
               <hi>Holines becommeth thy houſe for
<pb facs="tcp:405:23"/>
euer.</hi> The ſecond perſonall, as hee was a Chriſtian profeſſor of piety, and conformable to that commaun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dement, <hi>Eſay.</hi> 52.11. <hi>Be yee cleane that beare the veſſels of the Lord;</hi> &amp; both bee moſt requiſite in euerie ſpirituall Father. <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="1"/> Firſt, hee muſt keepe his locall purity in reſpect of the Church, whome hee muſt endeauour ſtill to preſerue and preſent, as a pure virgine vnto Chriſt, 2. <hi>Cor.</hi> 11.2. The Apoſtle foreſaw how hard a matter it woulde bee for <hi>Timothie,</hi> or any other in his place, to withſtand the importunate motions and violent perſwaſions ey<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther for ſparing the diſobedient from cenſures deſerued, or for preferring the inſufficient to places vndeſerued; therefore he dooth to preciſely inioin him to keepe his integrity in theſe af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>faires, vppon which the purity of the whole Church dependeth.</p>
            <p>
               <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="2"/> Secondly, <hi>Timothie</hi> muſt pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſerue
<pb facs="tcp:405:23"/>
his perſonall puritie in regarde of religion, whoſe chiefe commenda<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion is to be <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>, <hi>Iam.</hi> 27. <hi>pure and vndefiled;</hi> and ſuch ought all profeſſors thereof ſhew themſelues to bee; yet neither in the ſenſe of no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uatian heretikes,<note place="margin">Auguſt. de haere 38 ſ. cap</note> who fancied to them ſelues an impoſſible puritie, needing no repentance; nor of common hipo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>crites, which is that generation, that is pure in their owne conceite, though they be not waſhed from their filthi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe, <hi>Prou.</hi> 30.12. But the puritie here meant, is ſoundnes of faith and ſinceritie of manners, which as it was pictured in the high Prieſtes pecto<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rall, <hi>Exod.</hi> 28. by <hi>Vrim</hi> and <hi>Thummim;</hi> ſo is it chiefly required in <hi>Timothie,</hi> and all ſuch as occupie his place in the Church of God. Firſt, in regarde of his excellent order.<note place="margin">Dignitas ordinis.</note> The Philoſo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pher affirmeth, that all qualities be per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fecteſt in their firſt ſubiects; ſo is heate
<pb facs="tcp:405:24"/>
in fire, coldnes in water &amp;c. A Bi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhoppe is <hi>primum ſubiectum religionis;</hi> therefore his holines and vprightnes muſt exceede all other mens.</p>
            <p>
               <note place="margin">Vide Va<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tabl: not. ad hunc locum</note>The weightes and meaſures of the Sanctuarie, to witte, the ſicle, ta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lent and cubite; were of a double bignes to thoſe for common vſe, <hi>Ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>od.</hi> 30.13. euen ſo ſhould the vertues in the Miniſters of the Sanctuarie, be of a ſutable ſize. And this ſeemeth to bee implied in the ſacrifices for their ſinnes, appointed <hi>Leuit.</hi> 4. for there the prieſts offering is comman<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ded to bee as much as all the con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gregations, a young bullocke without blemiſh for the prieſt alone, ver. 3. and no more for all the people, <hi>ver.</hi> 14. <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="2"/> Secondly, this principall purity is enioyned <hi>Timothie</hi> for the counte<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nance and credite of Religion;<note place="margin">Counte<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nance.</note> for all pure thinges are more precious then mingled, as is euident in met<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tals
<pb facs="tcp:405:24"/>
and liquors, pure golde and ſiluer, pure wine and oyle, are in higher eſtimation, then when they bee mingled with baſer ſubſtance.<note place="margin">Scalig.</note> Now <hi>purum eſt quod nihil habet alieni.</hi> All ſtrangenes in Diuinitie is of a badde note and name, as ſtrange Gods, ſtraunge fire, and ſtraunge fleſh, and ſo are all ſtraunge opinions and condi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tions in the Profeſſors of it, as <hi>Eccleſ.</hi> 10.<hi>1.</hi> a little follie bee it mentall or morall, makes his re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>putation vnſauorie, that is in eſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mation for wiſedome and glory.</p>
            <p>Thus the baſe and corrupt car<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>riage of any man procureth diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>grace to himſelfe, and contempte of his place and profeſſion, whatſo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>euer it be in the ſtate ciuill or eccle<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſiaſticall.</p>
            <p>
               <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="3"/> Thirdly <hi>Timothie</hi> and his e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quals
<pb facs="tcp:405:25"/>
muſt keepe themſelues pure aboue other men, for the conti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nuance of Religion, becauſe the pureſt creatures are leaſt ſubiect to corruption, as is manifeſt in na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture: the celeſtiall bodies, ſtars and planetes continue in their ori<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ginall courſe, being free from all elementarie mixture. Corruption in euery thing is a forerunner of deſtruction: ſo on the contrary, the ſincerity of Religion is a ſingular meanes to preſerue it.</p>
            <p>To keepe Pietie in originall pu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rity, two duties are neceſſarie; <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="1"/> Firſt, information, ſecondly, reformatio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>. For information, the puritie of the Profeſſor is verie requiſite: Firſt, becauſe ſuch a one is more capable of the light of heauenly knowledge and fitter to conuay it vnto others, as is a cleare glaſſe, in admitting
<pb facs="tcp:405:25"/>
and tranſmitting the Suns beams: For certainely,<note place="margin">Mat. 5.8.</note> as <hi>the pure hearted ſhall ſee God:</hi> ſo there is reaſon, why they ſhould ſee furtheſt into the ſecrets of God, according to that, Pſalme 25.14. <hi>The ſecret of the Lord is reuealed to them that feare him: and his couenant to giue them vnderſtanding.</hi> Secondly, in regarde that innocency of life, breedes liberty of ſpeech, it falles out often that a corrupt teacher is many times tongue tied, but as the Grecians ſay, <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>, an honeſt heart cannot bee daunted in deliuering any truth.</p>
            <p>
               <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="2"/> For reformation of diſorders, which may tende to the decay of Gods worſhippe, the integrity of the chiefe Father and Gouernour thereof, is moſt auaileable, for though the ſtreames in a brooke
<pb facs="tcp:405:26"/>
be troubled or pudley, yet if the fountaine bee cleare, it will ſoone cleare them againe; and leſt any ſhould be diſcouraged with ſingle<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe in this kinde of ſinceritie, which the Apoſtle requireth ſo ſtrictly in this Prelate; <hi>Keepe thy ſelfe pure,</hi> (whatſoeuer become of others) as though <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>, one were none to doe anie good. Yes, ſaith a Greeke Fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther, in many caſes, <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>, one man truely zealous ſufficeth to reforme a whole mul<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>titude, not onely of the Laitie, but euen of the Clergie,<note place="margin">Zozomon lib. 2, cap. 14. hiſto, tripart,</note> as <hi>Paphnutius</hi> alone ſwayed the whole Councel of Nice, in the controuerſie con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cerning Miniſters marriage.</p>
            <p>Thus according to the charge
<pb facs="tcp:405:26"/>
laide vpon mee, I haue laide open the Apoſtles charge vnto you. God for his greate mercies ſake graunt vs all conſcience and grace, ſo to diſcharge it, as may be moſt for his glorie and our own good, through Ieſus Chriſt, to whome with the Father and the holy Ghoſt, bee aſcribed all honour, power, and prayſe, now &amp; euer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>more, Amen.</p>
            <trailer>FINIS.</trailer>
         </div>
      </body>
      <back>
         <div type="colophon">
            <pb facs="tcp:405:27"/>
            <p>LONDON Printed by I. VV for <hi>Mathew Law,</hi> and are to beſolde at his ſhoppe at the ſigne of the Foxe in <hi>Paules Churchyearde,</hi> 1607:</p>
         </div>
      </back>
   </text>
</TEI>
